בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, חודש טוב. Chodesh Tov. Today's דף daf is
דף ל"ו. daf lamed vav. We pick up in the top third
of ל"ה עמוד ב. lamed hey amud bet. We have now, we
had a whole series of cases like somebody said to his friend
what are you doing on my land and he said I've been
here three years and that led to an opportunity to explore a
wide range of conceptual הלכתי halachic issues not just limited to the
concept of חזקה. chazaka. Now we move on to the next phrase
of the משנה. mishnah. We're actually now moving our way through the
משנה mishnah now that we've laid a lot of the groundwork around
חזקה. chazaka. So at the two dots, a third of the way
down on ל"ה עמוד ב, lamed hey amud bet, חזקתן שלש שנים
יום ליום. chazakatan shalosh shanim yom l'yom.
So חזקה chazaka is three years from day to day and the
type of thing that's used on an ongoing basis. Best example would
be a home, a house. The גמרא gemara also spoke about an
irrigated field and so on. And we had other discussions if you
might remember about daytime and nighttime, if you have to testify to
the nighttime and do you have to literally be there every single
day etc. Now the גמרא gemara says like this: אמר רב אבא,
Amar Rav Abba, אי דארי ליה איהו גופיה טאנא דפירי לאלתר הוי
חזקה. idari lei ihu gufei tana d'peiri la'altar havei chazaka. If the
owner was seen, you know there's testimony to this, he was seen
carrying a basket of fruit, this guy's working in the land that
used to be my land or that you know was known to
be my land and there I was and I was carrying for
him a basket of apples with him to his truck. Okay and
people had testimony to that. So he doesn't have to prove he
was there three years. That's immediately immediate evidence. What the heck would
I be doing helping him שלעפ schlep a basket of apples to
his truck if it was not that he had bought it from
me? Right?
From that field.
Okay. So אמר רב זביד, Amar Rav Zevid, אם טען ואמר לפירות
הורדתיו, im ta'an v'amar l'peiros horaditiv, but if when I, my claim
is not that it is my field and I never sold him
to him, I don't know what he's doing there. Because what do
you mean don't know what he's doing there, you were seen bringing
this basket of apples to his truck. But if I say no
no no you don't understand, I rented it to him or you
know he's a sharecropper and he was on the field for the
fruit but I never sold him the land, then obviously the fact
that I was carrying a basket of fruit it does not hurt
my claim. Okay, so then I am believed. What?
אם טען im ta'an at any point? I'm sorry? Is it אם
טען? im ta'an?
Well if you first said I don't know what he's doing there
and then you backtracked then it would be a טוען וחוזר וטוען
to'en v'chozer v'to'en problem. Okay? So, but if you say it from
the outset then you were, you know then you would be, certainly
would be believed. Otherwise you'd have a טוען וחוזר וטוען to'en v'chozer
v'to'en problem. Okay. Now the גמרא gemara says like this: Okay, so
that's, so that's if you were seen carrying this basket of fruit.
והני מילי בתוך שלש. v'hani milei b'tokh shalosh. Now when am I
believed to say oh he's only there as a sharecropper you know
and that's why I was carrying this fruit, if he made that
claim and he's only been there less than three years. אבל אחר
שלש לא. aval achar shalosh lo. If he's been there more than
three years, with or without you helping with the fruit, Michael's been
on my land for three years and Michael says I bought it
from you I've been here three years and I say no what
are you talking about you're a sharecropper. Now that is a very
reasonable claim, right? There's a lot of reasons people are on my
land working my land, not because they bought it, right? Sharecropping, renting,
etc. So what do you do in that case? That now really
has little, very nothing to do with me carrying the basket of
fruit. Okay. So in that case if the הלכה halacha is that
I would not be believed. If I would be believed you could
throw every חזקה chazaka right out the door, right? I would always
claim that somebody was just there as a sharecropper. Now not necessarily
because I actually have a reason to claim that he's there illegitimately
rather than claiming that he's there as a sharecropper. Why would I
say that? Yes? The fruit. I get the fruit. Okay, so if
I think for some reason I can win by saying that he
was there completely illegitimately I'll say that. But if I know that
he's got real evidence that I you know that's kind of that
he was there three years and he harvested the fruit, so I
obviously if I would always be able to claim he was a
sharecropper right then you would undermine every חזקה. chazaka. So therefore I
am not believed after three years. But of course that then just
leads to the next question. What's the next question? Okay I'm not
believed. So what's the next question?
What if he really is a sharecropper? How do I defend right
my interest? So that's the next question of the גמרא. gemara. Okay.
So the גמרא gemara says like this: והני מילי בתוך שלש אבל
אחר שלש לא. v'hani milei b'tokh shalosh aval achar shalosh lo. אמר
ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, Amar lei Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana, אי
לפירא נחית מאי הוה ליה למעבד? i l'peira achtei mai havai lei
l'me'evad? So I don't understand.
Okay, if he genuinely is a sharecropper what is the owner supposed
to be doing? How is he supposed to protect his own interest?
He has to make a מחאה. mecha'ah. Now what type of a
מחאה? mecha'ah? So here the normal מחאה mecha'ah is you know is
that I get in front of two witnesses and I say Michael
is a גזלן, gazlan, he's on my land without any permission and
I want to make that as an official announcement. Okay. So the
גמרא gemara understands well that's not possible by sharecropping. So what are
your options? So the option is no no no you could still
say a מחאה mecha'ah but it would have to be a מחאה
mecha'ah of a different nature. I would go in front of two
people and say be aware that Michael's on my land as a
sharecropper or as somebody who rented the land and not as a
legitimate owner, I am making that as a public announcement. Now if
Michael actually is a genuine owner, right, and I'm trying to swindle
Michael here, he will hear that announcement and that will just require
him to be careful with his שטר. shtar. Okay, the same way
if I said he's a גזלן gazlan and I was lying, he'll
be careful with his שטר. shtar. So the חידוש chiddush here is
is that I can protect my interests by making an announcement. But
now of course it's very interesting, right? Until now we thought that
a מחאה machah would only occur if somebody was illegitimately on my
land. That's when I would have to make it unless I was
trying to obviously cheat somebody. Okay, now we're finding out that a
מחאה machah will occur in many legitimate situations, right? Anytime, and this
presumably was very, very widespread, that you would rent out your land
or you'd be or you'd let somebody be a sharecropper. And now
there will be a regular institution of making מחאות machot in order
to ensure that those, you know, that that to protect my interests
and for somebody for whom that מחאה machah is not legitimate, they'll
they'll know to hold on to their שטר. shtar. Yes.
Okay,
we say that the מחאה machah that we assume that the person's
going to hear because everybody's going to talk. Exactly. I can imagine
saying that oh, well, they'll only talk if they talk about a
thief. Right. But about a sharecropper in a regular business deal, why
would they talk?
Yeah, it's a very good point and that might be why the
גמרא Gemara is questioning, you know, whether a מחאה machah is even
possible or not. I mean I you know, it's a really good
question because you're right like it's not like oh, you know, the
better thing would have been to say that in cases of sharecropping,
I, if I'm making Michael a sharecropper, then I should get documentation
of that fact and hold on to documentation of that fact. Right,
because now what you're right is like if people aren't going to
talk as much about this מחאה machah and I'm a smart guy,
what I'll do is I'll sell my land, I'll make this מחאה
machah which will be not so talked about and then I'll go
and you know and everybody and and then I'll go and I'll
I'll get my land back from these people I sold it to.
Because now everybody who's a legitimate buyer has to have their ears
out not just for a מחאה machah that they're being called a
גזלן gazlan but for a מחאה machah that they're being called a
sharecropper. Yeah, you make a very good point and it helps us
understand why the גמרא'ס Gemara's grappling with this because, you know, because
yeah, it doesn't it's not as it doesn't protect it protects the
owner, it doesn't protect the buyer as much. That's absolutely correct. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says אי לאו תימא הכי, ei lav teima
hachi, now if you don't say that, if you say that that
type of a מחאה machah doesn't work, הני משכנתא דסורא, hanei mashkanta
desura, now
remember the משכנתא דסורא mashkanta desura which is I basically
Charlie borrows $10,000 from me and I'm going to take his his
field and hold on to that until he pays it off. But
actually what we're going to do is
this arrangement is going to actually let Charlie pay off his debt
because I'm going to hold on to his field for ten years,
I'm going to use them and harvest them and so on and
as and keep the produce and at the end of ten years
his debt will be paid off. Okay, now the חידוש chiddush here
of course is is that under normal circumstances those ten years of
produce are worth more than $10,000, they might be worth $20,000. But
we don't know that for sure, could be that there'll be flooding
or there'll be a drought or whatever it will be and I'll
get nothing. So it's not obvious ריבית ribbit and we view that
reframe what happens as less of a loan and more of a
type of a sale. I bought ten years of the fruit for
$10,000. Okay, but that's a משכנתא דסורא. mashkanta desura. So the גמרא
Gemara says now let's imagine I'm doing that and I'm on this
land and I'm harvesting for ten years and that was a classic
way of lending money and then paying off the debt. Why can't
I always just go ahead now and claim that I bought it?
Because I'm going to have three years of חזקה chazakah and who's
holding the שטר shtar in that case? I'm holding the שטר shtar
because Charlie owes me the money, right? So I so he doesn't
have any שטר shtar that proves that I'm there in a משכנתא
mashkanta situation, right? This is why you want two copies of a
contract, right? Because there'll be time when the when different sides have
to prove it and in הלכה halacha usually there's only one side
that has a copy of the contract. Okay, so how who's going
to prevent me from making that claim against Charlie's land? So אי
לאו תימא הכי, ei lav teima hachi, so Charlie, now that we
know there's a different type of a מחאה machah out there, not
just a מחאה machah the guy's a thief, but a מחאה machah
that the guy is there for different reasons. So one reason is
a sharecropper, one reason is it's a משכנתא, mashkanta, okay. אי לאו
תימא הכי ei lav teima hachi if you don't say that,
הני משכנתא דסורא, hanei mashkanta desura, דכתב בהו dechtav behu it's written
in the document, במישלם שניא אילין bemishlam shanya ilein at the end
of these years, תיפוק ארעא בלא כספא. tipok ara bela chaspa. This
land will go away go leave the control of the creditor, return
to the debtor, and then the debtor will be free of any
debt. The debt will be paid off. Okay, now אי כביש ליה
לשטר משכנתא ei kavish leh lishtar mashkanta
now I'm the one that's holding on to that שטר. shtar. Now
if I were to to hide that שטר shtar because I'm the
only one who has it, גבאי, gabai, ואמר לקוחה היא בידי, ve'amar
lekuachah hi beyadi, oh, I just bought this field off of Charlie.
So הכי נמי דמהימן, hachi nami de'meheiman,
so would I be believed? Right, this is a tremendous opportunity for
abuse. All these cases of משכנתא, mashkanta, a guy could just claim
it's his. So מתקני רבנן מידי דאית
ביה פסידא, matkini rabbanan midi d'it beih psida, this whole משכנתא דסורא.
mashkanta desura. with a rabbinic sort of institution, a way of dealing
with lending money and getting it paid up and dealing with ריבית
ribbis issues. How would we establish this if it was using even
this wide
gaping loophole that anybody who does it could just automatically claim they're
an owner? There must be a way that the debtor can protect
himself. So אלא איבעי ליה למחויי, Ella ibayei lei lemichuyei, it must
be that the debtor can make a מחאה, mecha, has to make
a מחאה, mecha, and that מחאה mecha will protect him. הכא נמי
איבעי ליה למחויי, Hacha nami ibayei lei lemichuyei, here too, the guy
lending out his field for sharecropping will actually can make a מחאה.
mecha. So the חידוש chidush here is that there can be a
מחאה, mecha, which because there are now we're realizing, hey, legitimate reasons
people are on other people's lands for long periods of time, okay,
and there's a way of making מחאה mecha for the owner of
the land to protect himself. Of course, as David is saying, that
just makes it a much harder system for people that buy land
because now, you know, the rumor won't go around as much that,
Dov, you know, people are saying you're a גזלן. gazlan. You know,
people are saying you're a sharecropper, people are saying you're a renter
or whatever, you know, that's not going to be the talk of
the town necessarily. So all the more reason people are going to
be that much more careful with their שטרות. shtaros. That's true. I
mean any type
of decision is going to more sort of benefit one side and
hurt the other side almost of the time, yes.
Losing, you know, a שטר shtar or whatever, there's a flood, there's
an accident.
Right.
Yeah, so that's a real problem. You have to be really careful.
So either you're out of luck or you're if you're able to
find the original עדים eidim and they still remember, you can write
a replacement שטר. shtar. Okay. The other interesting question in הלכה halacha
right is can you have multiple copies of the same document? And
you know, how does that sort of work? Because sometimes you can't
if you're afraid that somebody will be גובה goveh multiple times, but
if it's like like if it's a loan, right? But if it's
like multiple copies of a bill of sale, right? And they all
have the same date and they all say the same thing, then
that may be more possible, right? Alright.
So anyway, so let's how do they deal with partial payments of
loans, right? I mean shouldn't the person be getting like some kind
of receipt that indicates that...
Well, yeah, but if this, I mean, if the שטר, shtar, if
the שטר, shtar, if the שטר shtar says that Charlie owes me
$10,000, also says that I'm going to start with a משכון mashkon
starting on this date for 10 years and then I go in
on five years, that itself, the same document that proves he owes
me the money will also prove that it's been paid off partial.
But yes, there are receipts for partial payments, that is correct. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Can you write a replacement document with other witnesses if they were
also aware of what took place?
If they were directly present, not if they were only, right, not
only if they were aware because of... Now what if they saw
the שטר? shtar? Okay, that would be another. But if it's just
hearsay, that would not be good. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
ישראל הבא מחמת עובד כוכבים ומזלות הרי הוא כעובד כוכבים ומזלות. Yisrael
haba machmat akum harei hu ke'akum. If a Jew comes through a
non-Jew, which means, okay, Charlie, what are you doing on my land?
What are you saying, Dov? I bought it from Christopher. He says
he bought it from you. Okay, so in that type of a
case, his claim is only as good as the claim that Christopher
bought it from me, right? So
because maybe the non-Jew was lying. So, you know, I mean whatever,
maybe a Jew was lying, it's not the point, but having a
non-Jew, but the point is is that that is his חזקה chazakah
is no good. Why is his חזקה chazakah no good? So מה
עובד כוכבים ומזלות אין לו חזקה אלא בשטר, Ma akum ein lo
chazakah ella beshtar,
the same way if a non-Jew said that he bought my land
and I said what are you doing on and he says what
do you mean I bought it from you I've been here for
חזקה chazakah years, חזקה chazakah does not work for a non-Jew. He
has to he can only prove he bought the land with a
שטר. shtar. אף ישראל הבא
מחמת עובד כוכבים ומזלות אין לו חזקה אלא בשטר. Af Yisrael haba
machmat akum ein lo chazakah ella beshtar. Similarly, if Charlie is saying
he bought it from the non-Jew, if the non-Jew can produce a
שטר shtar or if we'll see in a minute if Charlie is
able to say that he saw the שטר, shtar, okay, and whatever,
then he would be believed, but if he's just saying I just
had his say so or I know he was there for חזקה
chazakah years, well since that did not establish him as the owner,
so in the end Charlie won't although he has a חזקה chazakah
and say, "Dov, this is I didn't own it why would you
be silent all these years?" My answer is I don't have to
give a reason. You have a חזקה שאינה מצד טענה. chazakah she'eina
mitzad ta'ana. You're basing your presence on it based on this other
person's claim and that other person's claim is unsubstantiated. His claim is,
you know, he just says he was there he has חזקה chazakah
years but that doesn't prove that he was owned it, you had
no right to assume he was the owner unless you saw a
שטר shtar and therefore your חזקה chazakah doesn't have a טענה ta'ana
because it's based on an unsubstantiated claim. Now why does a non-Jew
not have חזקה? chazakah? So here we have to get into the
reality that
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was everywhere.
Well, that's a good point. I mean it's
it doesn't distinguish although you could easily imagine that it might matter,
you know, where it is. So the basic reason is is because
of a case of an assumption that the non-Jews would be the
first of all they would be in the position of power against
the Jews and therefore they might sometimes seize fields and take fields
and the Jews would not be in a position to to be
מוחה moche because your מחאה mechah would not do any good or
they could get in trouble for making a fuss over something that
was seized especially what's seized by the government but maybe it was
just I don't know seized by the people in power you know
by the dominant population and not by the Jews that were the
minority population. So as a result their holding it for three years
would not be a חזקה chazakah because there's an explanation why I
was afraid to be מוחה. moche. Okay of course so that's the
explanation why a non-Jew does not have a חזקה. chazakah. So therefore
Charlie was not in a position to believe that claim and it's
a base so he's basing his claim on another unsubstantiated claim and
it doesn't work. Hold it a second I want to read a
few more lines because the גמרא Gemara will clarify it and then
you ask a question. So אלא בשלמא. Ela bishlama. אמר רב יוסף.
Amar Rav Yosef.
אמר ישראל Amar Yisrael now if Charlie says לדידי אמר לי אקום
דמינך זבנה. Lididi amar li akum de-minach zavnah. If the now first
the גמרא's Gemara's going to reject this in a minute. But one
minute that's only if Charlie bought it from the non-Jew without any
knowledge. But he says wait the non-Jew told me he had bought
it from you. מהימן Meheman he would be believed. So the גמרא
Gemara says wait why is that? Even
if- מי איכא מידי דאילו אקום אמר לא מהימן Mi ika midi
d'ilu akum amar lo meheman had the non-Jew said it he wouldn't
have been able to win that property from me if he if
the non-Jew said it directly.
So- לא מהימן. Lo meheman. ואילו אמר ישראל משמיה דאקום מהימן. V'ilu
amar Yisrael mishmeih d'akum meheman. So now that Charlie is saying what
the non-Jew would have said why does all of a sudden that
get more weight? Meaning at the end of the day okay that's
all fine we believe you Charlie that he said it to you
nobody's doubting you but the whole point is that that claim does
not win in court right? So so what if he said it
to you? Why should that make your claim legitimate? So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא אמר רבא Ela amar Rava so rather רבא Rava
says no. אי
אמר ישראל קמי דידי זבנה מינך וזבנה ניהלי Ei amar Yisrael kamei
didi zavnah minach v'zavnah nihali if Charlie claims no no no I
know that he was the owner I saw him buy it from
you or an alternative was I saw the שטר shtar you know
which was the legitimate שטר shtar I had direct knowledge that he's
the owner and וזבנה ניהלי v'zavnah nihali and he sold it to
me in that case מהימן meheman he is believed. מיגו דאי בעי
אמר ליה אנא
זבינתה מינך Migo d'ei baei amar lei ana zevintah minach since Charlie
has a מיגו migo he could say I bought it from you
and instead he's saying I bought it from the non-Jew who said
he bought it from you so- so okay now we're going to
believe Charlie's claim. So if Charlie- because he has a מיגו. migo.
He could just say he bought it directly from me. So if
the claim is I bought it from the non-Jew who said he
bought it from you we believe you we believe you bought it
from the non-Jew who said he bought it from you we just
don't believe that that non-Jew genuinely owned it okay? But if he
says I bought it from the non-Jew and I know that he
bought it from you or I saw evidence of that then we
believe that and therefore Charlie is the owner. David you had a
question before?
No you re-answered it. Okay yeah Mike. But if anything you know
it doesn't seem like such a good מיגו migo because he could
have said that but people would know especially a thing such as
the non-Jew owning it at some point in between would have a
קול kol so that could be potentially refuted so he wouldn't want
to say that because you know it's not necessarily a better טענה.
ta'anah. It wouldn't you know like me between us two you know
few people talk about oh my god Christopher got involved he stole
it you know?
Yeah it's an interesting question if we know that this guy was
on the land then and we know that through other evidence we
don't know that he was the owner but we know that he
was presenting himself as the owner. I don't know it's an interesting
question would that still be a מיגו migo that I could have
claimed- that he could have claimed he bought it directly from me
because since people don't presume that that means that he is the
owner- I hear the point it's a good point.
The other thing is you know let's say Christopher has a- had
a שטר shtar but like- but really thinking that these guys are
ruffians yeah he quote-unquote bought it from you like let's cover this
bleak act of theory put a veneer of honesty by a שטר
shtar but I only paid him a dollar for it and I
essentially you know stole it from you you know what I mean?
So like you know so- so we think the שטר's shtar's okay?
Like you know I- I mean how do we know that-
Well that's it you have to say that the claim of the
שטר shtar is that he- he could see that it was a
legitimate שטר. shtar. Yeah we're not concerned about that. All right. ואמר
רב יהודה. V'amar Rav Yehuda. Now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said האי
מאן דנקיט מגלא וטובילא ואמר איזיל איגזייה לדקלא דפלניא דזבנתיה מיניה Hai
man d'nakit migla v'tuvila v'amar eizil egzeiyeh l'dikla d'planya d'zavnteih mineih
so we saw this already somebody who takes a scythe and a
basket and says I'm going to go and cut down the- cut
the fruit the- the dates from somebody's palm tree because he sold
it to me מהימן Meheman we would believe it. לא חציף איניש
למיגזר דקלא דלאו דיליה. Lo chatzif inish l'migzar dikla d'lav dileih. People
are not believed to go ahead and to you know either it
means cut down the palm tree or to harvest the palm tree
that isn't theirs. So the point is that even though the person
has not yet done it by once he harvested it it's חזקה
דמטלטלין דכל דתחת ידיה דאינש דיליה הוא chazakah d'metaltelin d'kol d'tachat yadeih
d'inish dileih hu it's no longer קרקע karka it's מטלטלין. metaltelin. But
before he's done it then we would not sort of say oh
we have to protect this person's property no we would say somebody's
making this as a- as a- like a bold claim we're going
to assume that he's telling the truth. And those types of things
do happen people obviously do sell people the rights to collect their
fruit. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה. V'amar Rav Yehuda. Now רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda still said האי מאן דאחזיק מגודי דארודאי לבר Hai man d'achzik
migudi d'arudai l'var we're back to חזקה chazakah now. Okay somebody who
has a חזקה chazakah from גודי דארודאי gudi d'arudai basically means that
at the edges of the field outside of the fence of- of
my field there was like a little I guess a little buffer
zone that I left and sometimes the seeds would fall. All there
and animals would come and they would eat from that, you know,
it was on the other side of the fence. And let's say
some guy, what he's doing is all three years he's harvesting the
stuff that grows from those seeds in this little strip of land
outside of the fence. Okay, so it says, and I bought this
little strip of land. So that's not a חזקה. chazakah. Okay, לא
הוי חזקה. lo havei chazakah. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? מימר אמר,
meimar amar, כל דזרענא נמי עבודא אכלי ליה. kol d'zarna nami avuda
achli lei. Because I say, look, I'm not going to bother to
be מוחה moche if some guy is eating the fruit that sprouts
up in that little strip of land, because, you know, I'm not
going to get it anyway, the animals are going to eat it.
So, you know, I don't bother to be מוחה moche that stuff
is not going to be stuff I'm going to get a chance
to harvest regardless, and his eating it doesn't prove that he owns
it. Fine, somebody wants to eat it instead of the animals, let
them be my guest. Okay, now ואמר רב יהודה, ve-amar Rav Yehuda,
now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda also says, like these are a string
of statements of ואמר רב יהודה, ve-amar Rav Yehuda, which is why
they're together here. ואמר רב יהודה, ve-amar Rav Yehuda, and רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda also said, אכל ערלה אינה חזקה. achal orla eina chazakah.
If somebody eats ערלה orla fruit, it's not a חזקה. chazakah. There's
actually a different גרסא girsa that says הוי חזקה, havei chazakah, but
we'll go with the אינה חזקה eina chazakah point. Okay, which is
again, like, why do I care that somebody is eating my ערלה
orla fruit? I'm not going to be able to eat it anyway.
You don't need a חזקה chazakah for three years?
Yeah, but that doesn't count towards one of the years. Okay, and
so basically, this year it's all ערלה, orla, he eats it, that
does not count to one of the years. תניא נמי הכי, tanya
nami hachi, we taught similarly, אכל ערלה שביעית וכלאים אינה חזקה. achal
orla shevi'it ve-kilayim eina chazakah. So if he ate ערלה, orla, שביעית,
shevi'it, and כלאים, kilayim, אינה חזקה. eina chazakah. So ערלה orla and
כלאים kilayim is because basically why should I bother being מוחה? moche?
It's not going to be mine anyway. And שביעית shevi'it is because
also everybody has a right to it. Okay, so therefore that is
not a חזקה. chazakah. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, now that we're on this topic about
what type of fruit or produce is considered a חזקה. chazakah.
אכל שחסה לא הוי חזקה. achal shachas lo havei chazakah. שחסה shachas
is like fodder, it's like when the stuff originally grows, the corn
or whatever, the wheat. If you harvest it and cut it down
and then you can use it as fodder to feed your animals
and then it'll regrow. So you get like one harvest of fodder
and then the stuff just regrows. Okay, so if some guy came
in and he harvested all the שחסה shachas and then it all
regrew but you know and then he says, "Well, it's mine, I
took all the fodder for myself." So that's not a חזקה. chazakah.
Why not? Because the assumption is that why did you not wait
for it to grow to its full height? Why did you not
sort of harvest it at its full height? It must be that
you know you're not the real owner but so and you were
afraid to go and to do a real harvest, but to sneak
in and to do some quick harvest of the שחסה shachas that
was something you thought you could get away with. Like that's more
like what a thief does. They sneak in, they get some of
this and they run away. You know, you weren't really there in
a full presence to harvest it at its full growth. Okay, one
also wonders if I only harvested the שחסה, shachas, somebody else must
have harvested the full growth, which would then have challenged my claim.
It must be some scenario where I harvested the שחסה shachas and
it never grew and didn't regrow afterwards. Okay, but even so, because
I didn't wait for the full growth, and what normal owner would
not want to get the, you know, the שחסה shachas is worth
a trivial amount, what normal owner would not want to wait for
it to grow fully and to harvest it fully? So that undermines
my claim. אמר רבא, amar Rava, ואי בצירי מחוזא קאמר, ve-ee betzurei
mechuza ka-amar, but if it is in the valleys of מחוזא, Mechuza,
where presumably there they would use that area just for the purpose
of growing fodder, then הוי חזקה, havei chazakah, it is a חזקה
chazakah because that's actually what they would do there. אמר רב נחמן,
amar Rav Nachman, תפתיחא לא הוי חזקה. tafticha lo havei chazakah. תפתיחא,
tafticha, which רש״י Rashi says is like very hard, cracked, sun-baked land,
is not a חזקה. chazakah. Either because nothing really grows there, so
I don't really bother to protest if somebody manages to grow a
few seeds, big deal. Or the other explanation is if the sun
already makes the cracks in the land, it doesn't require plowing and
whatever, you just throw in the seeds. So therefore it's not the
same type of an ongoing process of growing the food. It's just
a more, but it's a funny idea because, you know, some things
require less work than others, right? Maybe if I have an orchard
that requires less work than if I'm growing wheat. But nevertheless, because
for wheat fields, you know, this is not the normal process, that
would be the other explanation. But the more simpler explanation
is that like very little grows there so it's not worth being
מוחה. moche. אפי כורא ועייל כורא, api kura ve-ayeil kura, if let's
say the land was
very non-productive
and therefore non-fertile and I for every, you know, pound of seed
I was able to harvest a pound of seed, okay, that's not
much of, that's like zero profit margin, a lot of effort for
zero profit. So in that case לא הוי חזקה. lo havei chazakah.
So it's not a חזקה chazakah because the owner can say, "Why
was I going to bother to be מוחה?" moche? Which by the
way is a little unfortunate. Let's say I'm the real owner of
the land and let's say it was a very, very bad harvest,
right, and I did not, you know, and I only got in
the same amount that I planted. Does that mean now I don't
have a חזקה chazakah claim on this land? So one wonders, you
know, if there would be a difference between if that's what happened
as based on circumstance, there was bad weather, there was a blight,
there was locusts, etc. So all the period while I was harvesting
it, I thought I was really going to take in a nice
harvest and then there was some circumstance, as opposed to a land
that, you know, what do they used to call it? Hardscrabble land,
I think they call it, you know, land that's very, the very
quality of it is such that it will never produce any real
profit. And in that type of a case, then, you know, that's
a different story. David, you wanted to ask something?
Yeah, I mean, how could it be, it must,
it certainly sounds like, if the גמרא Gemara is talking about where
you know it's going to produce, as opposed to where it doesn't.
Right, that's what I was saying, like, and that's like a type
of a land, אפי כורבי או אפי כורבי. apei kurevei o apei
kurevei. That seems to make the most sense. Of course, one could
still ask, even if I bought that land, how would I have
a חזקה? chazakah? Of course, why did I buy that land?
Maybe you wouldn't, you'd just have to hold on to the שטר.
shtar. Yeah, right. Or, or you need to use it in, for
some other purpose.
Right, and when I get a chance I'm going to build a
house on it, and until that point I'm planting some weeds and
whatever.
But if you build the house within two years and then you
don't need to worry about your שטר shtar anymore, because that's good
enough? Is that what you're saying? He said use it for some
other purpose.
Yeah, well, if I build a house, and being in the house
for three years is a חזקה. chazakah. Then I don't have to
have the purpose of getting a harvest.
Yeah, but like this is a question, let's say it was a
piece of land, right? And then, you know, and then you build
a house on it within one year, right? And then, you know,
then you...
Yeah, that's a good question. I was wondering about that as soon
as I gave that example. How much if I actually am not
just using the land, but actually like, what's it called, like, you
know, building on it, changing the land, maybe that could be a
חזקה לאלתר, chazakah le'altar, right? If you see me building a house
on your land, you're not going to wait for three years to
be מוחה. moche. Right, so maybe that's true. Maybe if I'm actually
doing some like, you know, major, what's it called, reconfiguration of the
property, changing the actual property itself, maybe there is a חזקה chazakah
faster. I'd have to look, but that makes a lot of sense
to assume there would be.
That's a really big deal.
I understand. Right. Exactly.
Until now we're talking just about use, we're not talking about actually
changing it. Let's say I go ahead and I knock down the
house that used to be your house because I'm going to build
a bigger one in its place. Like, one would imagine I would
have an immediate חזקה chazakah if you didn't say anything. All right,
anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this: והני דבי ריש גלותא. ve-hanei
de-vei reish galuta. Now, land that belongs to that, members of the
house of the ריש גלותא. reish galuta. Now you see it was
not just a non-Jew issue, it was an issue of those in
power versus those that were not in power. Okay, so the people
of the house of the ריש גלותא, reish galuta, those were Jews
and they were the ones who were part of the Jewish, sort
of, government and they had power, okay? And because they had power,
we were afraid to be, they might have taken it illegitimately and
we would be afraid to be מוחה. moche. So land that belongs
to them, or when dealing with them, לא מחזקינן בהו, lo machazikinan
behu, if they have land that's ours, they don't have a חזקה
chazakah claim, cause maybe they have it illegitimately and we're afraid to
be מוחה. moche. And similarly, ולא מחזקינן בהו, ve-lo machazikinan behu, if
we're possessing their land, we don't have a חזקה. chazakah. Now why
not? Right, if they have the power and we're there three years
and they're not מוחה. moche. So the רשב״ם Rashbam says, well, they
don't need to be מוחה, moche, they can always just, you know,
take it back by use of force. So therefore, their silence is
not an acquiescence because they're the ones in power. So at least
you see that it's equal opportunity here, it's not about Jews versus
non-Jews, it's about who's in power versus who's not in power. Yes,
Charlie?
What's the relationship of נחמן? Nachman?
Very close to the ריש גלותא.
reish galuta. Yes, and he has some interesting stories about how the
people that worked for him, were not always, for the ריש גלותא,
reish galuta, did unsavory things.
So does this mean they don't own any land legitimately? And they
have to have...
No, חזקה chazakah doesn't work. You have to hold on to your
שטרות. shtarot. Okay, ועבדים. ve-avadim. So now we look, we're actually now
going to more specific and concrete cases. We just had a whole
discussion about types of land and types of owners, but more about
types of, I mean, produce. And now we talk about other types
of things that you have חזקה. chazakah. So the משנה, Mishnah, amongst
the things in the משנה Mishnah it mentioned a house, it mentioned
an irrigated field, it also mentioned slaves, okay? So and slaves again,
it's not like normal מטלטלין. metaltelin. If I have, hold on to
Michael's iPhone here and I claim that it's mine, I'm believed. Thank
you very much, okay, this is mine now. Anyway, but מטלטלין, metaltelin,
but by land we said, you know, your, the, it's assumed to
belong to the original owner unless you have a שטר shtar or
חזקה. chazakah. And here the משנה Mishnah implies the same is true
about slaves, okay? Slaves also, they're not inanimate objects, well actually we'll
get to animals in a minute, but anyway, slaves also, they're connected
to land and their being in your house is not proof of
ownership. They're assumed to belong to the one we know the original
owner was unless you have a חזקה chazakah of three years. So
let's take a look about that in the גמרא Gemara and try
to see why that is. So the גמרא Gemara says, עבדים יש
להם חזקה? avadim yesh lahem chazakah? Do slaves have a חזקה chazakah
after three years?
והאמר רבה? ve-ha-amar Rabbah? Doesn't רבה... Rabbah... ואמר ריש לקיש? ve-amar Reish
Lakish? Doesn't ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say: הגודרות אין להם חזקה? ha-godrot
ein lahem chazakah? גודרות godros is a גדרות צאן, gidros tzon, flocks.
Flocks of sheep don't have a חזקה. chazaka. Now here by don't
have a חזקה, chazaka, he's not means three years. Again, this is
why the phrase חזקה chazaka is confusing, to be מוחזק muchzak means
also to be in physical possession. So while if I say that
Michael's iPhone is mine because I'm in possession of it, if Michael's
lamb, if Mary's little lamb happens to
be following me today to school and I say that it's my
lamb, I'm not believed. Why not? Why do you think as a
lamb is different than the iPhone?
Because the lamb could follow you.
Because the lamb could follow me, because actually the lambs walk around
on their
own, since they move on their own volition, and again, the presumption
is that they're not always like tightly watched and controlled, since they
move on their own volition, the fact that it's in my property
or I'm holding it is no proof that I took possession of
it. Maybe it just wandered into my field. Okay, so that's the
principle that גודרות godros don't have חזקה chazaka and presumably now, same
principle about slaves. Slaves could run away from a master, a cruel
master, or other reasons, or maybe the slave just came over to
my house to borrow a cup of sugar for his master and
I locked the door and then I claimed he was my slave.
Okay, so here slaves are not unique in terms of slave linked
to קרקע, karka, it's basically a claim that they move on their
own volition. So normal sense of physical possession does not suffice. So
the גמרא Gemara says, so one minute. Well, we're going to see
the answer. Okay, so that's immediate of physical possession. So גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אין להם חזקה לאלתר. ein lahem chazaka
le'altar. Right,
if you're just physically holding on to it, it doesn't work like
מטלטלין. metaltelin. The fact that you're immediately seizing it doesn't prove that
you're the owner. אבל יש להם חזקה לאחר ג' שנים. aval yesh
lahem chazaka le'achar gimmel shanim. After three years there is חזקה chazaka
because what is this sheep doing in my house for such a
long period? What is this slave doing in my house for such
a long period? Okay, so which is very interesting, which means that
the slaves in the משנה Mishnah are not the normal idea slaves
are like קרקע. karka. The slaves in the משנה, Mishnah, the same
הלכה halakha would apply to sheep. It's things that actually living things
that move on their own volition and that their movement is maybe
not tightly controlled. Okay, we'll get to tightly controlled in a minute.
Those types of a thing, whose property they're in does not prove
ownership. So then what does prove ownership? Right? What proves ownership is
the fact that I let my slave stay around in your house
for such a long time and I didn't say anything. I let
my sheep stay in your house for such a long time and
I didn't say anything. Okay, so in that type of a sense,
again, the silence, the lack of
מחאה mecha becomes the evidence. Now, it's a little different, I have
to say, in terms of slaves and sheep, because if you remember,
there are two things going on with classic חזקה. chazaka. One is
the silence of the original owner, and the other is—what's the other
component about that? Do people remember?
The claim that goes with that silence, but part of the factoring
also is the presence or the absence of a שטר, shtar, right?
That we sort of say, "Well, if you're within three years, produce
the שטר." shtar. But after three years I could say I don't
have the שטר. shtar. So that idea, that there's a factor of
the שטר shtar going on, works with slaves, which are sold by
שטר, shtar, they're also sold by כסף, kesef, just as קרקע, karka,
but we can assume that there would standardly be a שטר shtar
that went along with a slave. There would not under standard circumstances
be a שטר shtar that went along with sheep, right? So I
actually would say, and this makes a lot of sense, your sheep
is in my field for a year. Who needs three years? A
week, a month! What the heck are you doing letting—like, it's very
different if I'm, you have all these fields and I'm in one
field and you're not maybe taking track of exactly who's in your
field at a particular time. It seems a little different if I'm
holding on to a piece of your property in my house and
keeping it under my control, that it does not need you to
be silent for three years to prove that it's mine. It would
seem that a lesser period of time would be significant. Now by
a slave you could say maybe so, but where's your שטר? shtar?
So slave works out very well, right? That a) it's not immediate
possession isn't enough, the slave moves around, you need the silence of
the original owner, plus you need the three years maybe for me
to have a good explanation, "Where's my שטר?" shtar? But I think
at least for to me it would seem intuitively something like sheep,
a little bit less than three years, like a year would seem
to be more than enough. So it is interesting that it's like
one or the other, we don't have any middle position.
Yeah. I was going to say that also, I was going to
say it should depend upon how far away you are. If he
could follow you across the country, but a whole flock of sheep?
You know, like, how are they following you?
Right, exactly, and there's all these different factors. By the way, it's
not just sheep. There's another category that immediate חזקה chazaka doesn't work,
but maybe three years would work, which is דברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר.
devarim ha'asuyim le'hash'il u'lehaskir. Right? Like things that you normally lend out.
Michael's got a rake, okay, so... and he normally is always very
friendly, you know, or a lawnmower, very willing to lend it to
his neighbors. So then his lawnmower's in my house. I'm not immediately
believed to say it's mine because it's the type of thing we
know Michael lends out lawnmowers. Lawnmowers are things that people lend out
to their neighbors. Okay, so when would I be believed? Just three
years? Really? There's like no gap between one day and three years?
It requires three years. So it's a similar type of a question,
right? But those seem to be the two things we're moving to.
Standard מטלטלין metaltelin immediately, קרקע karka three years, מטלטלין metaltelin that direct
possession doesn't immediately prove or indicate ownership, it seems like we just
jumped to the three-year category. Okay, but by the slave that makes
a lot of sense because presumably there's a שטר shetar by a
slave as well.
Wait three years, what am I sorry what were we supposed to
do?
Let's say give it back to you? How would I if I
really did buy your
sheep and then it's within a year,
yeah, that's a good question. So what are you supposed to do?
I suppose you I guess you could write a שטר ראיה shetar
rayah even though you don't have a שטר מכירה. shetar mechira. You
have a שטר מכירה shetar mechira by קרקע karka and by a
slave, but by anything you can
write, I bought this sheep, was that sheep, I don't know.
I don't know, I guess that's why they brand it. Okay, but
you're right, you would need עדים edim or a שטר ראיה. shetar
rayah. You're right, that's a good point. All right, in a case
also where there was branding, that's an interesting question. Let's say I
branded my sheep, right? Would that be and you were silent about
it, but how did you know I branded it? Good questions. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
אם היה קטן מוטל בעריסה, im haya katan mutal ba'arisa, now let's
say this slave is an infant in a crib. So in that
case, יש לו חזקה לאלתר. yesh lo chazakah le'altar. Then I do
have חזקה chazakah right away because the infant did not get here
on its own accord. The only reason I'm holding onto this infant
is because I bought it. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, peshita,
isn't that obvious? It then becomes again it's not a formal category
of slave, it's a question of does it move on its own
volition or not? So if it's not moving on its own volition,
of course that should be evidence. No, לא צריכה דאית ליה אמא.
lo tzricha de'is lei ima. It has a mother. Everybody has a
mother, but presumably it means that normally it's with its mother, that
has a mother and the child haven't been separated and owned by
different owners. I mean that's the harsh reality of slavery. So מהו
דתימא ניחוש שמא אמו אייליתי' להתם. ma'u de'teima neichosh shema imei aylayteih
le'hasam. Maybe I would say, you know, maybe the mother was coming
over to borrow a cup of sugar or whatever and she was
cradling with her baby and she let her baby down and maybe
she left it there, you know, forgot it there or asked you
to watch it for a little while when she went to watch
an errand. So maybe it was brought there and not because you
purchased it, but in a way brought through its mother and your
possession does not prove ownership. So קא משמע לן אמא לא מנשיא
ברה, kamashmalan ima lo minashya breih, a mother does not forget her
child. Okay, she would not especially in a reality of a slave
society that a slave would leave their child with, you know, with
a slave owner, okay. All right, so therefore anyway that case we
say that it's again not about the formal category of slave, it's
about things that move on their own volition or not. הנהו עיזי
דאכלו חושלא. hanu izzei de'achlu chushla. Now there were some goats that
ate חושלא chushla which was some type of a produce
בנהרדעא be'naharda'a in Nehardea. אתא מרי חושלא. ata marei chushla. Now so
your goats, Charlie's goats were here eating, what does it say חושלא
chushla is?
Husk barley. Husk barley, there you go. Charlie's goats were eating my
barley in my field. Now they he would have to pay, you
know, שן, shen, the eating of in my field you have to
pay. But the problem is I'm not going to be able to
prove how much barley I had and how much they ate. Okay,
I think they ate like a thousand dollars' worth of barley and
Charlie's going to say, "You prove it to me. I'm claiming that
they only ate twenty dollars' worth of barley." המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. So what I so what I'm going to
do is I am going to seize the goats and now make
a claim against Charlie and I have a better position for to
my claim how much they ate because I'm in possession of his
goats. Okay, now so the גמרא Gemara says אתא מרי חושלא ata
marei chushla so the owner came, תפשינהו tashpinu grabbed hold of the
goats, וקא טעין טובא v'ka ta'ane tuvah and he was saying a
thousand dollars, that's how much you ate. אמר אבוה דשמואל amar abuha
de'shmuel said the father of Shmuel,
יילכו ליטון עד כדי דמיהן. yelcho le'itun ad k'dai demeihen. I'm believed
up to the value of the goats. Why? How does holding onto
the goats allow me to be believed in terms of how much
they ate? מיגו, migo, דאי בעי אמר לקוחים הם בידי, de'i ba'ei
amar lekuhu chasaym biyadi, because I could just say look I bought
the goats off of Charlie. So since I would be believed to
say I bought them off of Charlie
and so therefore I'm believed to say and they and take therefore
their full value to myself, I'm believed to say they ate up
to the value of what the value of the goats are. So
now the גמרא Gemara says והאמר ריש לקיש, v'ha'amar reish lakish, wait
a minute, didn't Reish Lakish say עיזי אין להם חזקה, ayzzei ein
lahem chazakah, why would I be believed? Don't we say that flocks
don't have חזקה? chazakah? And here there's no three years, I seized
them right away. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני עיזי דמסרינן
לרועה. shani izzei de'masrinan leroya. No, goats are different because they're handed
over to a shepherd. Apparently, I mean Rashi says it but he
doesn't say why, but apparently maybe goats are a little bit more
they run off or whatever the case might be. So people don't
just let as opposed to sheep which people sort of allow the
shepherd, you know, he lets the
sheep wander.
And you always make sure that there's somebody who's totally sort of
supervising and on top of them. Okay, because they'll run off. Again,
I don't know exactly why, but that's the claim. So therefore, even
though they move on their own volition, if they're constantly being supervised
and under somebody's control and watchful eye, then you can have a
חזקה chazakah for them. Okay, one does wonder even with a shepherd
that's constantly watching, every now and then a goat runs off, right?
So it's like, but okay, but presumably the likelihood of that is
less than with sheep. So the גמרא Gemara says one would have
imagined the same would be true about slaves as well. I mean,
you know, maybe it depends on the type of slave society. But
anyway, but how, but okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ואיכא—so v'ika
therefore holding on to them is evidence. ואיכא צפרא ופניא—one v'ika tzipra
u'panya minute, there are moments where they're not under anybody's watchful eye.
In the morning, they get sent out to the field, like the
shepherd apparently was waiting out in the field, and the owner would
release them and they'd go out to the shepherd, so there'd be
this gap of time when they were not under anybody's supervision. And
similarly in the evening, once they got back to town, presumably the
shepherd would let them go and they know to find their way
back to their owner. Okay, so there would be this gap of
period in the morning and in the evening when they weren't under
supervision. So the גמרא Gemara says בנהרדעא כיילא שכיחא. binhard'a kayla shechicha.
No, in this was talking about נהרדעא Nhard'a where there's a lot
of like nomads who are considered to be thieves and מידא לידא
משלמי mi'yada l'yada meshallmi and therefore there would never be a period
that they were not being supervised. They would be handed over directly
from the owner to the shepherd and the shepherd to the owner,
which once again shows it's not an absolute category, oh, flocks never
have חזקה. chazakah. It's based on the reality, similar to the whole
discussion about a baby slave, based on the reality of how much
do they move on their own volition unsupervised. Okay, but once they're
in that category and they don't have an immediate חזקה, chazakah, it
is interesting that it moves immediately into the three-year category. Even though
three years, the reason you need that long has something to do
with the presumption of the presence or absence of a שטר, shtar,
which is not really relevant here. Okay, so that's the issue about
slaves. Wait, Eli has a question.
Right, can you cause your own מיגו? migo? Like in this case
here where you don't—like you grabbed them and then you forced them
into like a מיגו migo situation.
You mean—you mean, is it what's bothering you that the grabbing should
be perceived of as theft?
I don't know, it's just—if
we saw him grab it and we perceived of it as theft,
then it wouldn't help him as a מיגו. migo. But he's just
holding on to them. You mean the point is that he's holding
on to them and he's saying you—they ate this much and I
took them because I want to get paid back from them.
Well, I'll tell you what also seems bothersome here, which is that
he might be saying ten thousand and it might be worth five
thousand. And we're going to say let's believe his claim up to
the value of the sheep. So we're going to use מיגו migo
but not to support the claim he made, but to support it
up to a certain point. I'm saying ten thousand dollars, I'm holding
on to this sheep. Oh, well we'll award you five thousand because
you could have said five thousand because you could have just said
the sheep were yours, right? So that's not exactly what I claimed,
right? So maybe I was claiming ten thousand because I wanted ten
thousand, you know, and I didn't want just want to claim five.
So yeah, I understand that there's something a little troublesome about this
מיגו. migo. All right, let's see the next case. Now we get
to the debate of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, which is, you'll remember, right? In a case of that it
was not an irrigated field, it was not a field that was
used year-round, it was something that went more with seasonal cycles. It
was a שדה הבעל, sde habaal, which means a rain-watered
field. So it had to go with the seasonal cycles. So רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said you don't need
a full three years because it's not used constantly. But what it
did seem they wanted is something that represented three years. So what
they—so what you had was you had the middle year, the middle
year was full, was twelve months, but the begin—the end of—but you
could suffice with the end of year one and the beginning of
year three. So for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that was three months
at the end of year one and three months at the beginning
of year three. And for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it was one
month and one month. And I still don't fully understand that just
because it's, you know, more natural cycles why that allows more a
representative three years rather than a full one. But that's anyway the
way it is. Okay, so and then there was a case that
sometimes even within one year if you had a field that had—that
had like different types of trees and, you know, you had one
harvest of grapes and one harvest of dates and one harvest of
figs, that you actually could three harvests even within one year, you
could actually get a חזקה. chazakah. So let's take a look. רבי
ישמעאל אומר שלושה חודשים. Rabbi Yishmael omer shlosha chodashim. לימא ניר איכא
בינייהו? Leima nir ika beinayhu? Maybe the difference between רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva about whether you need three months
for those partial years or one month is the question about whether
plowing, you know, ניר nir would be a plowing that you would
do in a year you had let it lay fallow. It would
be a turning over of the soil. Maybe that's a better sort
of way of saying it. It's
a... Does that count? Maybe that's the issue. For רבי ישמעאל סבר
Rebbe Ishmael savar ניר לא הוי חזקה nir lo hava chazakah doesn't,
so you need a full three months to get some harvest out
of the land. רבי עקיבא סבר Rebbe Akiva savar ניר הוי חזקה
nir hava chazakah and therefore you only need one month. So הגמרא
haGemara says אי הכי ei hachi does that make sense? לרבי עקיבא
מאי איריא חודש? LeRebbe Akiva mai irya chodesh? If tilling was enough,
then who needs a whole month? אפילו יומא חד נמי, afilu yoma
chad nami, you could till it all in one day. Right? You
need time for stuff to grow. I mean obviously you need time
depending on how big the amount is, but it wouldn't be a
month. However, so you could till it in a few days, that
would also count if tilling was enough. אלא דכולי עלמא ניר לא
הוי חזקה. Ela dechulei alma nir lo hava chazakah. Fine, tilling is
not enough and for the reason that as we'll see, like you
have to actually get profit from what you're doing. Okay, so you're
tilling it. I'm not going to be מוחה mocheh you're tilling my
land. Thank you very much. Okay, so that's not a חזקה. chazakah.
הכא פירא רבא ופירא זוטא איכא בינייהו. Hacha peira raba upeira zuta
ika benaihu. The difference is whether you were talking about like substantial
fruit that needs a three-month cycle. That's what רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael
says, you have to actually produce some fruit of substance. And רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva says even some small produce. The רשב"ם Rashbam suggests
maybe the small produce is like the שחת shachas that we saw
earlier, just some type of fodder, even stuff that grows within a
month. Okay, so that's the difference, how substantial of a produce, but
ניר nir itself would not be enough. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, now
we're going to shift to this discussion about ניר. nir. ניר אינו
חזקה. Nir einu chazakah. ניר nir is not a חזקה. chazakah. ויש
אומרים הרי זה חזקה, Ve'yesh omrim harei zeh chazakah, some say it
works. It is a חזקה. chazakah. מאן יש אומרים? Man yesh omrim?
Who is those that say it works? אמר רב חסדא רבי אחא
היא, Amar Rav Chisda Rebbe Acha hi, it's רבי אחא. Rebbe Acha.
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, נירה שנה neira shana
you allowed it to lay fallow or you tilled it for one
year, וזרעה שתים uzra'ah shtayim and then the second year you plant
for two years you planted, you tilled for one year then you
planted for two, or נירה שתים וזרעה שנה neira shtayim uzra'ah shana
you let it lay fallow for two years or you tilled it
for two years and you planted for one, אינה חזקה eina chazakah
that doesn't work. Meaning even for one year ניר nir doesn't work.
רבי אחא אומר הרי זו חזקה Rebbe Acha omer harei zo chazakah
does work. Now תוספות Tosafot says two years tilling in a row
would not work even for רבי אחא. Rebbe Acha. The case of
רבי אחא Rebbe Acha that it would work
is you tilled it, you planted it, you tilled
it year one, you planted year two, and then you tilled it
year three. Because then we could say you're alternating years of tilling
and planting and so on. But tilling two years in a row
makes no sense, no normal owner does that. Okay, but anyway רבי
אחא Rebbe Acha says it does work because in the context of
a planting the tilling is seen as what an owner does. An
owner sometimes tills it and lets it lay fallow. So if you
have at least one year, it's a big חידוש, chiddush, even one-third
of the years, one year of planting, that gives a context for
the tilling and that frames you as the owner. Okay, that's what
רבי אחא Rebbe Acha says, but the חכמים Chachamim disagree. You need,
that's not sufficient provocation for the original owner to say anything. אמר
רב אשי שאליתיס כל גדולי הדור, Amar Rav Ashi sha'alitus kol gedolei
hador, I asked all of the גדולי הדור. gedolei hador. You see
the idea of a גדול הדור gadol hador is already in the
גמרא. Gemara. I asked all the גדולים Gedolim ואמרו לי ניר הרי
זו חזקה, ve'amru li nir harei zo chazakah, a ניר nir is
a חזקה, chazakah, it works. אמר ליה רבי ביבי לרב נחמן, Amar
lei Rebbe Bibi leRav Nachman, I have no
idea, מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר ניר הוי חזקה? mai ta'ama deman de'amar
nir hava chazakah? What's the reason that a ניר nir is a
חזקה? chazakah? לא עביד איניש דכריבו ליה לארעיה ושתיק lo avid inish
decharivu lei le'araia veshatik because people don't see other people tilling their
land and not saying anything because tilling, even though you're not gaining
anything from it, you're acting as if you're the owner. And that
is enough of a provocation. ומאי טעמא דמאן דאמר ניר לא הוי
חזקה? Umai ta'ama deman de'amar nir lo hava chazakah? What's the reason
it's not good? מימר אמר Meimar amar because the owner can say
to himself כושיכא ושיבא כושיבא ושיבא דחריבו ליה באגא kushicha veshiva kushiva
veshiva decharivu lei be'aga every thorn and thistle and every sort of
thing that the guy's going to plow, let it go into his
plow. Meaning thank you very much for tilling my land and using
your equipment or whatever and then I'll come in and I'll step
in later. Which basically means, so what are they arguing about? Are
they arguing about whether people object?
So the debate, some say people do object, some say people don't
object. It seems like
everybody agrees that you are a little bit showing yourself to be
the owner and you are providing a provocation and normally I would
object. But that my side, even though a normal person would object,
silence is not significant enough, is not a significant enough proof. Because
there's an explanation for the silence. Yes it's true, normal people they
see somebody tilling their land, they're going to yell and scream. But
I had a good reason not to yell and scream. I figured
you go ahead and you do all the work and I'll step
in later. So both could be true. It could be true that
normal people will object and it could be true that I have
a good explanation why I didn't object and my silence doesn't prove
that you're the owner. Okay? So
what?
Okay. So where were we? Okay. שלחו ליה בני פום נהרא לרב
נחמן בר רב חסדא. Shalchu lei benei Pum Nahara leRav Nachman bar
Rav Chisda.
So the people of this place of this river, by the edge
of the river, they sent Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda, ילמדנו רבינו.
yelamdenu rabbeinu. ילמדנו רבינו, yelamdenu rabbeinu, let our master teach us. ניר
הוה חזקה או לא הוה חזקה? nir havei chazakah o lo havei
chazakah? Is it good or not? אמר ליה, Amar lei, רב אחא
וכל גדולי הדור, Rav Acha ve-chol gedolei hador, אמרו ניר הוה חזקה.
amru nir havei chazakah. He said again, כל גדולי הדור, kol gedolei
hador, רב אחא Rav Acha and all the גדולים gedolim said it
is a חזקה. chazakah. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said, רבותא
למיחשב גברי? Rabuta le-michshav gavrei? Oh, you think it's a big deal
just to list names? כל גדולי הדור, kol gedolei hador, you know,
whatever. It's not about listing names or about invoking the גדולים. gedolim.
It's not about invoking the גדולים, gedolim, it's about listing names. It's
about who's gonna make a stronger argument. And anyway, I'll give you
my list of גדולים. gedolim. My names are better than... I don't
know. רב נחמן בר יצחק? Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak? That's a good
question. I don't know. Anyway, he says, הא רב ושמואל בבבל. Ha
Rav u-Shmuel be-Vavel. Oh, you want names? I got names. רב ושמואל
בבבל Rav u-Shmuel be-Vavel and רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא בארץ ישראל. Rabbi
Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva be-Eretz Yisrael. So some of the greatest אמוראים Amoraim
in בבל Bavel and the greatest תנאים Tannaim of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael אמרי ניר לא הוי חזקה. amri nir lo havei chazakah.
They say ניר nir doesn't count. Now how do you know this?
So,
רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא מתניתין, Rabbi Yishmael Rabbi Akiva matnitin, that's our
משנה, mishnah, 'cause they both say you need one month or three
months. And remember we said that if ניר nir worked, it would
work in one day. Why do they need a month or three
months? 'Cause they need a real harvest. ניר Nir is not enough.
So that shows they hold ניר nir is not a good. Okay,
so that's then. Now, רב מאי, Rav mai, where do we see
that רב Rav says ניר nir doesn't work? דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, De-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, זו דברי רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא.
Zu divrei Rabbi Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva. This idea of one month or
three months, that's the opinion of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim omrim, חזקה ג' שנים
מיום ליום. chazakah gimmel shanim mi-yom le-yom.
You need three full years even in an irrigated field. You don't
have these idea of partial years. So מיום ליום, mi-yom le-yom, למעוטי
מאי, le-ma'utei mai, what's it coming to exclude? לאו למעוטי ניר דלא,
Lav le-ma'utei nir de-lo, it must be excluding the case of just
tilling, then you would not need full. Now, of course you could
say maybe you need three full calendar years but during the entire
calendar year you have to be tilling it and plowing, you know,
and overturning the soil every day. But presumably that doesn't make any
sense, like that's, that's silly. Nobody does that throughout the year. So
if you need a full year it means that you've got to
use it in the way field is used throughout a year which
is through normal planting and harvesting and not through overturning the soil.
So if we rule you need three years, clearly the overturning the
soil is not sufficient.
Now, ושמואל מאי, u-Shmuel mai, what's שמואל? Shmuel?
Where were we? מאי? Mai? דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, De-amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel, זו דברי רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא. zu divrei Rabbi
Yishmael ve-Rabbi Akiva. Same idea, this idea of one month or three
months, that's their opinion. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim omrim, but the
sages say, עד שיגדור שלש גדירות ויבצור ג' בצירות וימסוק ג' מסיקות.
ad she-yigdor shalosh gedirot ve-yivtzor gimmel betzirot ve-yimsoq gimmel mesiqot. That you,
it's not enough to do just some quick little one month or
three months type of a harvest. Is it, it is a type
of a thing that, you know, is about dates, you need three
full date harvests, you know, if it's a type of something about,
that's יגדור, yigdor, is about collecting the dates from a palm tree.
If it's about the thing about grapes you need three full grape
harvests. If it's about olives you need three full olive harvests. It's
not enough to have a quick once or three months harvest in
the beginning or the end. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? Now what's
the difference by the way between רב Rav and שמואל? Shmuel? רב
Rav says three full years, שמואל Shmuel says three full harvests. So
there's an obvious difference. Three full harvests doesn't have to take three
full years. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב דקל נערה
איכא בינייהו. Amar Rav dekel na'ara ika beinaihu. A young palm tree
which can produce harvests in, you know, in quicker than in a
year. So according to שמואל Shmuel it's three full harvests, not three
full years. But either way, they don't, neither of them says that
just overturning the soil is enough. I'll just say one more very
important sentence at the end here. So they now say, let's deal
with רב Rav for a minute. רב Rav says three years from
day to day. So now there's a very important רשב"ם, Rashbam, this
to conceptualize, you know what? Maybe I'm gonna hold off of that
because I'll, I'll begin with it tomorrow. Okay, so now we've decided
ניר לא הוי חזקה, nir lo havei chazakah, but what we've also
ended with is a question of in the end of the day,
do you need three full calendar years? And have we completely rejected
the רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא Rabbi Yishmael Rabbi Akiva approach at the
end of the משנה? mishnah? That's what רב Rav says. Or according
to שמואל, Shmuel, you still
three harvests still work, but you can't have a super short harvest,
you need like three full harvests. Okay, so we'll talk about that
tomorrow, talk about the implications about that in terms of how the
very mechanics of חזקה chazakah actually work. So to be continued tomorrow.